Cole and Ambler Hat Manufacturers Records
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Cole and Ambler Hat Manufacturers Records.
1852-1886.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Center.
Cole and Ambler Hat Manufacturers.
2.5 linear feet.
MSS19910041
Cole and Ambler was one of the more than twenty hat manufacturers in Bethel, Connecticut during the nineteenth century.
History
Cole and Ambler was one of the more than twenty hat manufacturers in Bethel, Connecticut, during the nineteenth century. [Edward J. Gallagher, History of Bethel, Connecticut, New Haven: Technical Planning Associates, 1969, p. 2-10.]
Little secondary source material concerning the company has been located, and the reliability of what has been found is questionable. A History of Bethel, Lewis and Laura Goodsell, eds., (1976), state only that Cole and Ambler burned down in 1805 [p. 43]. It is possible that either the manufacturing building was destroyed at this time, and that the company re-established at another location, or that the date in the book is wrong and the company was burned out at a later date. Since the Cole and Ambler records start fifty years after the company was supposedly destroyed, the Bethel reference cannot be true as published.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of financial records of the company such as journals, ledger and accounts received and paid in addition to payroll and employee accounts. Also included are Sales records and ordering materials.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Connecticut business records. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Hat trade—Connecticut—19th century.; Connecticut—Business, industries, and trades—Hats.; Bethel (Conn.)—Business, industries, and trades—Hats.
Document Types:
Administrative Records; Financial Records.
Occupations:
Hat manufacture.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Unknown.
Detailed Description
- Series I: General Accounts, 1852- 1886
  - Ledgers
    - 1852 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - 1867-1870 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - 1870-1874 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
    - 1875-1886 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Journals
    - 1870-1872 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
    - 1882-1885 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Daybooks
    - 1867-1868 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
    - 1883-1886 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Lot book
    - 1867-1869 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Accounts
    - 1868-1869 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
    - 1869-1873 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
    - 1871-1874 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
    - 1874-1881 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
    - 1875-1877 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
- Series II: Personnel Records, 1868-1885
  - Employees' Account book trimmers, 1868-1885 (Box 2:, Folder 15-18)
  - Employees' Account book, 1870-1885 (Box 2:, Folder 19-22)
- Series III: Sales Records, 1856-1875
  - Sales
    - Daily sales, 1856-1871 (Box 2:, Folder 23)
    - Shipping book, 1867-1869 (Box 2:, Folder 24)
    - Shipping book, 1869-1872 (Box 2:, Folder 25)
  - Orders
    - Order book, 1868-1873 (Box 2:, Folder 26)
    - Order book, 1873 (Box 2:, Folder 27)
    - Order book, 1873-1874 (Box 2:, Folder 28)
    - Order book, 1874-1875 (Box 2:, Folder 29)